A Guide to the Walter Gropius/G. Preston Frazer Papers, 1969-1992
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Walter Gropius/G. Preston Frazer Papers, 1969-1992
Special Collections, Virginia Tech, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms1992-052
0.3 cu. ft. 1 box
The collection contains correspondence (from Mrs. Walter Gropius to G. Preston Frazer), as well as photographs, newsclippings, and publications about Gropius.
Frazer, George Preston
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
The Walter Gropius/G. Preston Frazer Papers were donated to Special Collections in 1992. Additional negatives and contact sheets were donated in 2014.
Biographical Information
Walter Gropius (1883-1969) was a renowned German-American architect; director of the Bauhaus from 1919 to 1928 and Chair of the Harvard University Graduate School of Design from 1938 to 1952.
G. (George) Preston Frazer was born in Davidson, Tennessee, February 4, 1908, to George Augustine and Sadie (Warner) Frazer. He received a BA in Liberal Arts from the Virginia Military Institute in 1929. In 1935, he completed a BS in Engineering at the University of Hawaii, and in 1937, a Masters of Architecture at Harvard University. During World War II, he served with the Second Armored Division in Europe and North Africa. He remained in the Army Reserves until 1968. From 1939 to 1940 and from 1946 to 1974, he taught in the Art Department of Virginia Tech. Following his retirement, Frazer continued to support Virginia Tech, which continues to be among the many institutions to display donations of his work. Frazer died at his home in Catawba, North Carolina, on September 10, 2003.
Scope and Content
The collection contains correspondence, mostly from Mrs. Walter Gropius to G. Preston Frazier, as well as photographs of the Walter Gropius bust at Virginia Tech and events surrounding the dedication. The collection also contains publications and clippings about Gropius and his work.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged by material type.
Index Terms
Persons:
Gropius, Walter, 1883-1969
Subjects:
University History; Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University. College of Architecture
Contents List
- Correspondence, 1969-1992 (Box-folder 1:1)
  - Letter from Charles Burchard to Preston, December 2, 1969
  - Postcard from Jean to Preston, December 7, 1969
  - Letter from Mrs. Gropius to Mr. Frazer, December 11, 1969
  - Letter from Charles Burchard to Frazer, Carter, Sevely, December 19, 1969
  - Letter from Mrs. Gropius to Mr. Frazer, February 21, 1970
  - Postcard to Preston, March 6, 1970
  - Letter from "Grope Fest" to Mr. Preston Frazer, May 14, 1970
  - Letter from Mrs. Gropius to Mr. Frazer, December 13, 1970
  - Letter from Mrs. Walter Gropius to Mr. Frazer, October 15, 1972
  - Letter from Mrs. George A. Frazer to Preston Frazer, November 1, 1972
  - Letter from Charles Burchard to George P. Frazer, October 24, 1977
  - Letter from Charles W. Steger to George and Bea, April 20, 1992
- Photographs, 1969, n.d (Box-folder 1:2)
  - 4 slides of Gropius bust (Box-folder 1:2)
  - 15 unidentified photographs (Box-folder 1:2)
  - 4 photographs from the presentation of Gropius bust, December 9, 1969 (Box-folder 1:2)
  - 4 8x10 photographs of Gropius bust (Box-folder 1:2)
  - Walter Gropius Bust Dedication Events, Negatives (photographs by John Carnochan), 1969 (Box-folder 1:5)
  - Walter Gropius Bust Dedication Events, Contact Sheets (photographs by John Carnochan), 1969 (Box-folder 1:6)
- Publications, 1963-1969 (Box-folder 1:3)
  - "Magister Gropius." Reprinted from September 1969, Progressive Architecture
  - V.P.I. Daily Bulletin, Vol. 18, No. 41. Wednesday, December 3, 1969
  - Walter Gropius-architect-creator-educator. An exhibition of the works and creations of Walter Gropius. Arranged by the Bahaus Archive, Darmstadt with support of the foreign office of the federal Republic of Germany
- Miscellaneous, 1968-1970 (Box-folder 1:4)
  - Speech given by Mrs. Gropius
  - Photocopy of article on Grope Fest
  - Western Union Telegram to Professor Marvin Sevely and Professor Preston Frazer from Grope Fest, May 8, 1970
  - Advance for feature article in the newspaper, The Star Ledger
  - Newspaper article about Gropius. The New York Times, July 6, 1969
  - Newspaper article about Gropius. The New York Times, July 8, 1969
  - Harvard University: The President's Report, 1968-1969